Finding Aid for Henry Philip Tappan papers, 1840-1936
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Philip Tappan papers 1840-1936 1840-1881
Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.
1 linear foot (in 3 boxes) and 2 oversize folders
86101 Aa 2; Ac; UAm
First president of University of Michigan. Correspondence, essays, sermons, lectures, poetry, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the Graduate Library of the University of Michigan (donor no. 1278 ), with an addition in 2013 from Marguerite O. O'Connell (donor no. 9477 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Henry Philip Tappan, first president of the University of Michigan, was born at Rhinebeck on the Hudson, New York on April 18, 1805. He graduated with a B.A. degree from Union College in Schenectady in 1825, then received a divinity degree from Auburn Theological Seminary in 1827. In 1828, he was ordained a minister of the Congregational Church, but medical difficulties shortened his ministerial career allowing him time to travel. From 1832 to 1837, Tappan was professor of moral and intellectual philosophy at the University of the City of New York.
Prior to coming to the University of Michigan in 1852, Tappan lived and studied abroad, becoming acquainted with the progressive and scholarly traditions of European universities. As president, Tappan was responsible for the growth of the University, for improving the quality of faculty, and for the founding of the Detroit Observatory. Tappan also faced opposition to his leadership from the Board of Regents and in 1863, he was asked to resign. The remaining years of his life were spent in Switzerland, where he died November 15, 1881.
The Tappan papers include addresses, lectures, sermons, poems, biographical material, list of books in the Tappan library, and correspondence. The correspondence deals with his scholarly interests, particularly in philosophy and education, his travels in Europe, and University of Michigan matters. Tappan's correspondents include James B. Angell, Thomas M. Cooley, Victor Cousin, Edward P. Evans, Alpheus Felch, Samuel F. B. Morse, Charles H. Palmer, Julia Livingston Tappan, and Andrew D. White. A separate group of correspondence is addressed from Tappan to his friend and financial advisor Edwards Pierrepont. There is also correspondence about Tappan particularly between Charles M. Perry and graduates and officials of The University of Michigan, and three volumes of manuscript poems by Tappan.
Subjects:
Poetry.; Clergy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. President.
Subjects: Visual Materials
Medals.; Monuments and memorials.; Sculpture.; Switzerland.; Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Cousin, Victor, 1792-1867.; Evans, E. P. (Edward Payson), 1831-1917.; Felch, Alpheus, 1804-1896.; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872.; Palmer, Charles Henry, 1814-1887.; Tappan, Julia Livingston.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sermons.
- Correspondence
  (microfilm copy of most of the correspondence is available)
  - 1840-1863 (Box 1)
  - 1864-1870 (Box 1)
  - 1871-1877 (Box 1)
  - 1878-1881 (Box 1)
- Correspondence with Edwards Pierrepont
  - 1855-1866 (Box 1)
  - 1867-1869 (Box 1)
  - 1870-1880 (Box 1)
- Biographical
  - Letters of Charles M. Perry re Henry P. Tappan, 1909-1938 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Collected materials of Charles M. Perry re Henry P. Tappan, including copies of Tappan letters (Box 1)
  - Letters to James B. Angell and Alfred H. Lloyd from Henry W. Rankin concerning in part Tappan, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Auction list (Folder Ac)
  - Detroit Daily Advertiser articles (Folder Ac)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - List of books in Tappan's library (Box 2)
- Essays, addresses, etc.
  - Moral philosophy: include "A Course of Moral Philosophy" and manuscripts on philosophy and ideas on universities (Box 2)
  - John Milton, essay on (Box 2)
  - Manuscript of essay "Psychology", 2 folders (Box 2)
    (include typescript version)
  - Sermons, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Poetry (Box 3)
  - Translation of "Nibelungenlied" (Box 3)
  - Poetry and manuscript volumes of poetry, 3 volumes and 1 folder (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Portraits (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Switzerland; and photographs of sculptures and other Tappan memorials (Folder UAm)
    (in oversize folder UAm)